Rakesh Chouhan

Lead Software Engineer

US | Ph: +1 337 853 1497 | me@rakeshchouhan.com

Summary

A little over 13 years of progressive software development experience with expertise in design, development, program & system analysis, testing & application integration. Ability to increase reliability, maximize productivity and system efficiency. Genuine commitment to quality and client satisfaction. Passionate to learn and adopt new technologies.

Work History

Capital Group, Irvine, CA (WFH - Charlotte, NC)

Apr 2020 - Present

Lead UI/Java Engineer

Capital Group is one of the world's largest investment management organizations serve individual investors, financial intermediaries and institutions around the world through a broad range of products and services. I worked on Preliminary Fee Quote that helps clients chose the right retirement 401k plans. I was later transitioned to Retirement Plan Services Application which is currently being revamped into Retirement Plan Application Modernization using latest cutting edge technology.

Wells Fargo, Charlotte, NC

Apr 2019 - Mar 2020

Sr Microservices Engineer

As a SWIFT GPI enabled bank, Wells Fargo is held accountable to SWIFT and its customers for timely status updates on GPI payments and is graded by SWIFT on timeliness of messaging and payment processing. This project will work on ability to send payment status updates via the API Connector which speeds up response times for the status updates. Also it provides real time access to customer GPI payment status, improving our Observer scoring, which is visible to our customers

Compass Group, Charlotte, NC

Oct 2016 - Mar 2019

Sr Software Consultant

OMS(Owners Management Suite) comprises of multiple microservice applications that leverages a distributed systems pattern providing diverse services to external and internal clients. This application incorporates clustered cache & storage architecture, data lake for analysis & metrics, etc. and front end UI written in ReactJs

Goldman Sachs. Jersey City, NJ

Jan 2015 - Oct 2016

Sr Principal IT Consultant

The Expense Management Application supports Goldman customers to raise Invoices for their monthly businesses. It allows the customers to Self Service themselves with followings tasks like, assigning Invoices to Analysts, Coders, Reviewers, Administrators, etc.

VMware. Palo Alto, CA

Mar 2014 - Mar 2015

Sr Principal Software Engineer

The vSphere Web Client enables you to connect to a vCenter Server system to manage an ESXi host through a browser.

The VCSA Installer (aka. vCenter Server Appliance) deployer is used to run the vCenter Server, where the user's can easily install and configure vCenter without the need of having a dedicated server. This product was first developed in Windows Client, which was again packaged as a Linux based VM. Currently this product goes as a standalone application which provides the same functionality as the Windows Client.

Links

Personal Website

https://rakeshchouhan.com or https://react.rakeshchouhan.com

LinkedIn

https://linkedin.com/in/chouhanrakesh

https://github.com/chouhan

Wordpress

https://chouhans.wordpress.com

Skills

ReactJs 16.x/17.x

AngularJS 1.5/2.0/4.0

NodeJS

Javascript & TypeScript

HTML 4/5 & CSS 3

Java/J2EE & Scala

Spring-boot Micro Services & **Distributed Systems**

RDBMS & NoSQL

Big Data Ecosystem

Hadoop/Spark/Kafka

Morgan Stanley. New York City, NY

May 2012 - May 2013

Linux & Unix Shell scripting

Sr Software Engineer Consultant - Remote

Capital Budgeting (CB/Wallet) and Technology Funding Requests (TFR's) are flex based internal dashboards of Morgan Stanley to maintain Funding Management of various clients across the world. These dashboards are also intended to serve the workflow status of each request made. FAM (Funding Alert Management) dashboard was intended to serve the Business Owner's, the Super Departments to view and or take an appropriate action (CRUD operations) on a Wallet or a TFR.

Web/App Servers

GIT/SVN/TFS/Perforce

Deloitte. Harrisburg, PA

Jul 2011 - Feb 2014

Sr IT Consultant

ASSIST/COMPASS is an online application for Delawarians/Pennsylvanians to apply for many health & human service programs. The fast and easy way to apply for various benefits - anytime and anywhere. Benefits Include, Health Care Coverage, Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program (SNAP), Cash Assistance, Long Term Care, etc..

CAFE (Common Access Front End) is developed for the Department of Children and Family Services (DCFS) for State of Lousiana. The Rich Internet based CAFE application, serves the residents of lousiana to opt welfare programs for Child Care & Family while selecting various Benefits. CAFE application is purely a browser based application.

Skills & Concepts

Technologies: Apache Kafka, InMemory Computing & InMemory DB (Apache Ignite), Design Patterns, Application Security (Basic, OAuth 1.0/2.0, CAS), Authorization, Spring-Boot, Hibernate/JPA, REST & SOAP WebServices, , D3.js, Mocha, Chai, Bootstrap UI, ReactJs, Angular & AngularJs, Karma-jasmine, GraphQL.

Cloud: Networking & Virtualization Concepts, IaaS, PaaS, SaaS, Unix/Linux, Elastic Load Balancers, Azure, Amazon Webservices (AWS), Heroku, Circle CI, Docker, Vagrant.

Distributed Systems: RDBMS & NoSQL Databases (Redis, MongoDB, MemCached, CassandraDB), Neo4J, Hive, PIG Latin, HBase, Scalability, Fault Tolerance, Fail Fast, Consistent Hashing, Resilient Distributed Datasets (RDD's), Apache NiFi, Zookeeper.

Tools: Adobe Campaign, Adobe Experience Manager, NPM, Grunt, Webpack, Maven, Gulp, Gradle.

IDE's: Intellij Idea, Eclipse, Visual Studio Code, MuleSoft.

Methodologies: Agile, SAFe, Scrum, Scrum of Scrum & Waterfall.

Chrysler (FCA). Auburn Hills, MI

Apr 2010 - Jun 2011

IT Consultant

wiTech Vehicle Diagnostic Application serves as the core and the integral software to inspect all the Chrysler Vehicles and is currently being used by all the Chrysler Dealers across the world.

Verizon. Irving, TX

Feb 2009 - Apr 2010

Software Engineer Consultant

Template Manager for sending emails is used for internal Business employees of Verizon Telecom which is based on Apache Flex as the UI and J2EE as the server side. This project is mainly intended to make the Business more user friendly. Template Manager is used to send promotional, billing dues and offers as emails to the corresponding preferred customers of Verizon.

Volunteer Experience

Cox Communications

Oct 2019 - Mar 2020

POC for Cox communications via Capgemini on Email Marketing tool using Adobe Campaign to send promotional emails to client's end users.

Adobe Systems Inc

Jul 2017 - Sep 2017

POC for T. Rowe Price via Adobe Systems Inc on Email Marketing tool to send promotional emails to client's end users.

Hortonworks

Aug 2015 - Oct 2015

Application demo to re-model an ideal RDBMS IDE/Workbench like MySQL/SQL Server editor into a rich interactive and intuitive GUI Application, for Hortonworks internal users.

Expertise

- Software Application Development
- Service-Oriented Architecture (SOA)
- Enterprise Implementations
- B2B Integrations
- Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC)
- QA & UAT Management
- Release Management
- Offshore Development Operations
- Production Support
- Team Building and Management

Education

Masters in Electrical and Electronics Engineering. Jan 2008 - May 2009

Wayne State University. Detroit, MI, USA

Bachelors in Electronics & Communications Engg. Jul 2003 - May 2007 Aurora College of Engineering. Hyderabad, Telangana, India